听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们已经讨论了复制
So, we've been talking about replication.
如果你还记得的话 我们在上一节课讨论了广播协议
And if you remember, in the last lecture, we talked about broadcast protocols.
广播协议的核心是
And the whole point of a broadcast protocol is
让所有的节点都按照某种顺序接收一组消息
for all of the nodes to receive some set of messages in some order.
复制的核心是让所有的副本都可以处理相同的更新请求
And the point of replication is for all of the replicas to process some updates.
你可能会问
So, you might be wondering
我们能不能使用广播协议来实现复制
hmm, shouldn't we be able to use a broadcast protocol to do replication.
你的想法是对的
And you would be right.
事实上 我们确实可以使用广播协议实现复制 我们现在来看具体方法
Indeed, we can use broadcast protocols, and we're going to look at that now.
首先 我们从FIFO全序关系广播出发
So, first of all, let's start with FIFO total order broadcast,
这是我们考虑的最强大的广播协议
the strongest of the broadcast protocols which we considered.
如果你还记得的话 全序关系广播的核心是
And if you remember, the point of total order broadcast is that
所有节点都将按照相同的顺序传递相同的消息集合
all of the nodes will deliver the same set of messages in the same order,
而这正是我们想要的复制
which is exactly what we want for replication.
这种方法叫做状态机复制
And this approach is called state machine replication.
算法非常简单
So, the algorithm is simple.
当一个副本想要更新自己的状态时
Whenever a replica wants to make some update to its state,
它使用FIFO全序关系广播向其他所有副本广播更新操作
it uses FIFO total order broadcast to broadcast that update to all of the replicas.
当一个副本收到其中一个更新操作时
And whenever a replica delivers one of these updates,
它处理此更新操作 将更新操作应用在自己的状态上
it processes that update, applies it to its own state.
此副本将从广播中收到的更新操作看作是更新函数 用此函数更新自己的状态
So, it updates its own state as a function of this update that it received over the broadcast.
这一方法之所以可行的一个关键点是
And the key thing that makes this work is that
执行更新操作的逻辑是确定性的
the logic for applying an update is deterministic.
因此 你可以把每个副本看成是一个状态机
And so, you can think of each replica as a state machine.
副本的状态就是副本存储的所有数据
The state of the replica is all of the data that it has stored.
每个副本的都以固定的启动状态启动
And every replica starts off in a fixed starting state,
启动状态一般是一个不包含任何数据的空数据库
which is usually an empty database containing no data.
随后 副本进行确定性状态更新
And then, the deterministic state update means that
也就是说 当两个副本处于相同状态 而我们又给它相同的输入时
whenever two replicas are in the same state, and we give them the same input
两个副本将会转移到相同的下一个状态
then they will transition to the same next state.
因为FIFO全序关系广播可以保证
And because FIFO total order broadcast ensures that
每个副本都按照相同的顺序传递相同的更新操作
each of the replicas delivers the same updates in the same order,
如果我们以这些传递的更新操作作为状态机的输入
if we take these delivered updates to be the input to the state machine,
则对于每一个副本
then on each replica,
其状态机都会按照相同的状态转移顺序进行状态转换
the state machine is going to go through the same sequence of state transitions,
按照相同消息顺序处理完毕后
and they're both going to end up in the same state
每一个副本都将在相同的状态下终止
after they've processed the same sequence of messages.
这正是我们想要的状态机复制
So, this is exactly what we want of state machine replication.
这是一种非常好的复制方法
And it's a very good way of performing replication,
因为只要我们有全序关系广播
just because if we have this total order broadcast,
复制算法本身就会变得非常简单
then the replication algorithm itself is really simple.
每当出现执行一次更新操作 我们就通过全序关系广播来广播此更新操作
It's just whenever we have an update, we broadcast it via total order broadcast.
每当传递了一次更新操作 我们就依此操作完成更新
And whenever we deliver an update, we update the state accordingly.
实际上 这个思想被广泛应用于
And this idea is actually very widely used
多种不同的复制系统中
in a whole range of different replicated systems.
举例来说 有些分布式数据库
So, there are some distributed databases, for example,
使用此方法来复制事务
which use this approach for replicating transactions,
这些数据库的状态更新逻辑可以变得特别复杂
so, this logic here of the updating the state, as long as it's deterministic,
只要求状态更新逻辑是确定性的
it can be any arbitrarily complex logic.
你可以将包含任意业务逻辑在内的整个事务都打包在一起
So, you can package a whole transaction including arbitrary business logic into this,
并保证所有事务
and make sure that the inputs to the transactions
都通过全序关系广播传递给所有的副本
get delivered to all of the replicas through total order broadcast,
这样一来 你就可以在每个副本上独立执行事务
and then, you can independently execute this transaction on each of the replicas,
它们都将在相同的状态下终止
and they will end up in the same state.
这一原则非常有效
Very nice. Very nice principle.
区块链、分布式账本、智能合约等所有这些领域
Very similar principle underlies blockchains, and distributed ledgers,
都使用了类似的原则
and smart contracts, and all of this area.
你在区块链中得到的是一系列区块构成的链条
What you have in a blockchain is a chain of blocks.
实际上 区块链条就是
And this chain of blocks is actually exactly
通过全序关系广播协议传递的一系列消息
the sequence of messages delivered by a total order broadcast protocol.
系统应用一个共识机制来实现全序关系广播
So, there's a consensus mechanism around implementing this total order broadcast.
一旦有了全序关系广播 后面要做的只是按照特定的顺序
But once you've got it, it's just a sequence of transactions or updates or jobs
执行一系列交易、更新或任务
that need to be performed in a certain order.
每个副本将按照相同的顺序处理这些确定性的事务
And each replica will process those deterministic transactions in the same order.
因此 它们都将在相同的状态下终止
And therefore, they will end up in the same state.
区块链中的状态构成了一个账本
And in this case, the state constitutes a ledger
此账本告诉我们谁持有哪个货币
saying who owns which coins, for example.
状态机复制的缺点
Now, the downside of state machine replication
就是全序关系广播的缺点
are the downsides of total order broadcast.
如果你还记得 我们在介绍全序关系广播时说过
So, if you remember when we were looking at total order broadcast, we said that
当一个节点想广播一条消息时
when a node wants to broadcast a message,
它不能立刻将此条消息传递给自己
it cannot immediately deliver that message to itself.
它必须与其他节点协调好
It has to coordinate with the other nodes
以决定各个副本传递消息的顺序
in order to decide the order in which the replicas are going to deliver the messages.
这一过程也被用在状态机复制中
And the same applies here with state machine replication.
也就是说 副本不能立刻更新自己的状态
So, that means the replica cannot immediately update its own state.
它需要通过全序关系广播处理更新操作
It has to go through the total order broadcast process
从而知道更新操作的执行顺序
in order to know the order in which these updates are going to get applied.
这也意味着我们需要使用全序关系广播协议
And it does mean that we need a total order broadcast protocol.
我们将在下一节课学习如何实现全序关系广播
We will study that in the next lecture.
另一个全序关系广播原则应用在复制的例子是
Another example of how this principle of total order broadcast is used for replication is
数据库的被动复制
in what is called passive replication for databases.
在这个例子中
And so, what happens here is that
你有一个主节点数据库和一个或多个从节点数据库
you have got a leader database and one or more follower databases.
如果你还记得 我们在讲解全序关系广播时说过
And if you remember what we said about total order broadcast,
有一种实现全序关系广播的方法是
one way that you can implement total order broadcast is
指定一个节点作为主节点
by designating one node as the leader.
主节点将决定消息顺序
And that leader is going to decide on an order of the messages,
随后 所有其他节点
and then, all of the other nodes are going to deliver the messages
将按照主节点广播的顺序传递消息
in the order they were broadcast by the leader.
这也正是数据库复制中所发生的情况
And this is exactly what happens in database replication.
在数据库复制中
So, in database replication,
一个客户端向主节点请求执行某个事务
you've got one client which requests the leader to execute some transaction.
可能另一个客户端
And maybe another client
也在同时请求主节点执行某个事务
can currently request the leader to also execute some transaction.
主节点可能会并发执行这些事务
And those transactions might execute concurrently on the leader.
我们一般要求 如果事务涉及修改数据库状态
We do have usually the requirement that only the leader can execute transactions
则只有主节点才能执行此类事务
if those transactions are going to modify the database state.
可以在从节点上执行只读事务
So, any read-only transactions could execute on the followers,
但只有主节点可以执行读写事务
but any read-write transactions have to execute on the leader.
虽然主节点会并发处理事务 但事务会按照全序关系提交
Now, transactions may execute concurrently, but they will commit in some total order.
提交顺序在这里起到了非常重要的作用
And this commit order is the crucial thing here,
因为当提交一个事务时 提交日志中会追加一条记录
because when a transaction commits, then a record is appended to the commit log,
此记录描述了事务修改了哪些数据
saying what were data changes that were made by this transaction.
此提交记录会通过全序关系广播发送给所有从节点
And this commit record is sent to all of the followers via total order broadcast.
随后 所有从节点也将应用提交的事务
So, then, all of the followers will apply the transaction commits,
按照提交顺序依次执行事务并修改数据
and the data changes from each transaction in the commit order.
这样一来 我们仍然沿用了相同的原则
And so, again, we've got the same principle,
所有主节点和所有从节点都按照相同的顺序执行提交的事务
all of the leader and all of the followers are applying the commits in the same order.
因此 它们会经历相同的状态转移顺序
And so, they go through the same sequence of state transitions,
这里使用的原则与状态机复制的原则是相同的
again, using the same principle as a state machine replication.
这就是全序关系广播的使用方法
So, that is using total order broadcast.
这显然是实现复制的一个好方法
It's clearly a good way of implementing replication.
我们还讨论过稍弱一些的广播类型
We also discussed weaker forms of broadcast.
我们讨论过因果关系广播、FIFO广播
So, we discussed causal broadcast, and FIFO broadcast,
可靠广播、以及尽力广播
reliable broadcast, and best-effort broadcast.
我们能否使用这些广播类型实现复制呢？
So, can we use those as well for implementing replication?
答案是：可以实现 只是使用时要更小心一些
And the answer is, yes, we can. It just requires a little bit more care.
这里我们需要用到交换律这一概念
So, one concept we need for this is commutativity.
我们称 如果可以按照任意顺序执行两个更新操作
And so, we're going to say that two updates are commutative
则称这两个更新操作满足交换律
if you can apply them in either order.
无论是先应用f再应用g、还是先应用g再应用f
So, either you apply first f, then g, or you apply first g, then f,
无论按照何种顺序执行这两个更新操作 最终的执行结果都是相同的
and the end result is the same, no matter in which order you apply these two updates.
很明显 并不是所有的更新操作都满足交换律
Now, clearly, not all updates are commutative.
如果我们想让更新操作满足交换律
We have to specifically design the algorithm
我们必须为更新操作设计专门的算法 使其满足交换律
for updates to be commutative if we wanted to be commutative.
不过 确实有可能设计出满足交换律的更新操作
But it is possible to design updates in such a way that they are commutative.
如果我们能设计出满足交换律的更新操作 我们就可以使用因果关系广播
And if we do that, then, for example, we can use causal broadcast.
当使用因果关系广播实现复制时
So, with causal broader broadcast,
我们还要求更新过程是确定性的
we also require that processing update is deterministic.
所有基于广播的复制模型都要求更新过程满足确定性
That is still a requirement of any of these broadcast-based replication models.
回忆一下 因果关系广播所能提供的顺序保证是
But then, remember that the order guaranteed provided by causal broadcast is
如果一条消息在另一条消息之前发生
if one message happened before another,
则这两条消息会按照此前发生顺序传递
then those messages get delivered in their happens before order.
但两个并发消息可以按照任意顺序传递
But two concurrent messages might be delivered in either order.
因此 如果我们想要保证所有副本处于相同的终止状态
And so, if we want to ensure that all of the replicas end up in the same state,
我们必须保证 对于任意两次并发更新操作
then we must ensure that for any two updates that are concurrent,
其对应的状态更新函数必须满足交换律
their state update functions must commute.
如果满足这个条件 则意味着任意不满足交换律的状态更新操作
And so, if we have that, then that means that any non-commutative state updates
必须按照正确的顺序通过因果关系广播发送
will be provided in the right order by causal broadcast,
任何可能会被因果关系广播重排序的更新操作必须满足交换律
and any updates that might be reordered by causal broadcast are commutative,
这样我们才能按照任意顺序执行这些更新操作 并得到相同的最终状态
and so, therefore, we can apply them in either order, and will end up in the same state.
我们可以进一步泛化对广播的要求
Now, we can generalize this further,
可靠广播无法保证消息的传递顺序
and with reliable broadcasts, we have no ordering guarantees at all,
我们只能保证所有消息会恰好传递一次
we just have the guarantee that every message is delivered exactly once.
这种情况下 我们必须要求所有的更新操作都满足交换律
And so, in this case, we have to have all of the updates, they must commute,
因为广播协议无法提供任何顺序保证
because the broadcast protocol provides no ordering guarantees.
我们可以进一步弱化对广播的要求
And we could go even weaker.
我们甚至可以使用尽力广播
So, we could even go to best-effort broadcast,
这种情况下 我们甚至无法保证
in which case, we're not even guaranteed
一条特定的消息会被传递多少次
any particular number of deliveries for a certain message.
消息可能会丢失 也可能会被多次传递
So, a message might be lost, or it might be delivered multiple times.
这种情况下 状态更新函数必须能够容忍消息丢失
So, in this case, the state update function will have to tolerate message loss,
状态更新函数必须满足幂等性
and it will have to tolerate
以容忍消息被多次传递
messages being delivered multiple times through idempotence.
但你可以看到 所有不同的广播模型
But you can see that actually all these different models of broadcast,
都可以用于构建复制系统
we can use in order to build replication systems.
这就是本节课的全部内容了
So, that's all for this lecture.
在下节课中 我们将会深入探讨一些细节
In the next lecture, we're going to drill into some more detail on
学习如何以一种可靠的方式实现全序关系广播
how actually we implement this total order broadcast in a way that is reliable.